Guide to the Yusef Komunyakaa Papers
Beinecke Rare Book and Manuscript Library
Yusef Komunyakaa papers
1930-2014
1976-2014
JWJ MSS 152
Beinecke Rare Book and Manuscript Library
35.21
(49 boxes)
Komunyakaa, Yusef, 1947-
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Purchased from Chris Calhoun Agency on the James Weldon Johnson Memorial Collection of Negro Arts & Letters Fund and the Edwin J. Beinecke Book Fund, 2014.
Conditions Governing Access
The materials are open for research.
Box 48 (audiovisual materials): Restricted fragile material. Reference copies may be requested. Consult Access Services for further information.
Box 49 (digital media): Restricted fragile material. Access copies of digital files may be requested. Consult Access Services for further information.
Biographical / Historical
Yusef Komunyakaa is an African American poet and recipient of the 1994 Pulitzer Prize for poetry.
Scope and Contents
The collection consists of writings, correspondence, writings of others, other papers, printed materials, audiovisual materials, and electronic media that document the life and work of African American poet Yusef Komunyakaa. The writings and correspondence are intermixed with writings of others and other papers that collectively document Komunyakaa's poetry, writings, teaching, and personal life. Printed materials include clippings, writings by Komunyakaa, and promotional materials. Audiovisual materials include audio and video recordings of Komunyakaa.
Arrangement
Organized into five series: I. Writings and Other Papers, 1930-2009. II. Correspondence and Other Papers, 1976-2014. III. Printed Materials, 1970s-2000s. IV. Audiovisual Materials, undated. V. Electronic Media, undated.
African American poets -- 20th Century; American literature -- 20th Century; Authors, American -- 20th Century; Poets, American -- 20th Century -- Archives; Audiovisual materials; Born digital; Authors, American -- 20th Century; Poets -- United States -- 20th Century; Komunyakaa, Yusef, 1947-
- Writings and other papers, 1930-2009; Series I; 10; (10 boxes)
  - Holograph notes, drafts, correspondence, photographs, and other papers, 1930-1999 (Box 1)
  - Holograph notes, drafts, correspondence, and photographs, 1980-1992 (Box 2)
  - Holograph notes, drafts, correspondence, and printed material, 1980-2001 (Box 3)
  - Holograph notes, galley proofs, correspondence, teaching materials, and printed materials, 1991-2002 (Box 4)
    Scope and Contents
    Includes a proof of Talking Dirty to the Gods.
  - Holograph notes, typescripts, drafts, and other papers, circa 2005 (Box 5)
  - Typescripts, writings of others, and correspondence, 1997-2000 (Box 6)
    Includes drafts of Komunyakaa's Shangri-La, Blue Notes, and Thieves of Paradise. Also includes two pieces of mail art from Reetika Vazirani.
  - Typescripts, holograph notes, drafts, writings of others, printed materials, correspondence, and other papers, 1980-2009 (Box 7)
  - Holograph notes and drafts, 2000s (Box 8)
  - Holograph notes, drafts, typescripts, galley proofs, writings of others, and other papers, 1973-2005 (Box 9)
    Includes typescripts and galleys for Thieves of Paradise, Magic City, Dien Cai Dau, I Apologize for the Eyes in My Head, and Dream and Spleen: Uncollected Early Poems 1973-1976.
  - Holograph notes and drafts, 2000-2005 (Box 10)
- Correspondence and other papers, 1976-2014; Series II; 25.88; (30 boxes)
  - Correspondence, promotional materials, and other papers relating to events, readings, and publications, 1980-1999 (Box 11)
  - Correspondence, clippings, printed materials, and other papers relating to academic events and publications and holograph notes and drafts, 1998-2002 (Box 12)
  - Academic and professional correspondence from Indiana University and Princeton, 1990-2009 (Box 13)
  - Correspondence and other papers, mostly relating to Komunyakaa's Pulitzer Prize, 1985-1994 (Box 14)
  - Professional and personal correspondence regarding events and academic service, 1986-1996 (Box 15)
  - Correspondence, writings of others, academic papers, and other papers, circa 1990s-2000s (Box 16)
  - Writings of others, teaching and research materials, and related correspondence, undated (Box 17)
  - Writings of others and related correspondence, circa 2000s (Box 18)
  - Professional correspondence, promotional materials, writings, and notes, 2002-2006 (Box 19)
  - Professional correspondence and other papers, 2002-2006 (Box 20)
  - Professional correspondence and other papers, 1976-2009 (Box 21)
  - Professional correspondence and other papers, 1990s-2000s (Box 22)
  - Writings of others, typescripts, printed materials, flyers, correspondence, and notes and drafts by Komunyakaa, 1990s-2010s (Box 23)
  - Manuscripts sent for review, invitations, appearances, events, and notes, 2012-2014 (Box 24)
  - Correspondence relating to events, appearances, and awards, writings submitted by others for review, and notes by Komunyakaa, 1990-1999 (Box 25)
  - Correspondence relating to events, travels, readings, and appearances, writings submitted by others for review, 2000-2009 (Box 26)
  - Correspondence relating to events, travels, readings, appearances, and academic events, printed materials, and writings submitted by others for review, 2000-2009 (Box 27)
  - Correspondence relating to events, appearances, and academic events and printed materials, 2000-2009 (Box 28)
    Includes piano/vocal score for "Slip Knot" Opera with music by T.J. Anderson and libretto by Komunyakaa.
  - Correspondence, flyers, faxes, announcements, typescript pages, and writings of others, 2002 (Box 29)
  - Correspondence, flyers, faxes, announcements, typescript pages, and writings of others, circa 2002 (Box 30)
  - Correspondence relating to events, flyers, itineraries, receipts, notes, and typescripts, 2000-2002 (Box 31)
  - Correspondence relating to events, flyers, clippings, and notes, 2001-2006 (Box 32)
  - Correspondence relating to events, flyers, clippings, and notes, 2001-2006 (Box 33)
  - Correspondence relating to events, flyers, clippings, and notes, 1990-1996 (Box 34)
  - Correspondence relating to events, academic work, and publications, flyers, clippings, announcements, and other papers, 1990-1994 (Box 35)
  - Correspondence relating to events, academic work, and publications, flyers, clippings, and printed materials, 1984-1996 (Box 36)
  - Professional correspondence, notes, flyers, clippings, printed materials, and other papers, circa 2003 (Box 37)
  - Professional and personal correspondence, notes, flyers, clippings, printed materials, and other papers, 1996 (Box 38)
  - Professional correspondence, writings of others, and other papers, 1996-2005 (Box 39)
  - Professional correspondence, writings of others, notes, drafts, and other papers, 1991-2005 (Box 40)
- Printed materials, 1970s-2000s; Series III; 1.41; (7 boxes)
  - Periodicals, 1970s-2000s (Box 41)
  - Periodicals, 1970s-2000s (Box 42)
  - Clippings, including Komunyakaa writings, circa 1980s-2000s (Box 43)
  - Calendars and poster, 1990s (Box 44)
  - Calendar and printed material, 1990-1999 (Box 45)
  - Posters, broadsides, and publications, circa 1996 (Box 46)
  - Posters and printed material, 1990s-2000s (Box 47)
- Audiovisual materials, Series IV; 0.42; (1 box)
  Conditions Governing Access
  Restricted fragile material. Reference copies may be requested. Consult Access Services for further information.
  - Apinana Taylor, "Whakapapa" / Parihaka, "The Art of Passive Resistance", undated; 1; 01:22:11; The program is distorted at times. (Box 48, Item barcode 39002099362734)
  - Elisabeth Kuhn's Reading, 2000 September 19; 1; 00:32:19; The program is distorted at times. (Box 48, Item barcode 39002099362742)
  - Yusef Komunyakaa, UCSD, 2001 April 18; 1; 00:54:38; A high amount of hiss can be heard on the tape. (Box 48, Item barcode 39002099362759)
  - "The Real Deal", undated; 1; 00:27:23 (Box 48, Item barcode 39002099362767)
- Electronic media, Series V; 0.42; (1 box)
  Restricted fragile material. Access copies of digital files may be requested. Consult Access Services for further information.
  - 4 Compact Discs (Box 49)
- Books and serials, 1; (1 box)
  - Books and serials (Box A)